To turn off the order button if the form is invalid, I need to find out if my overall form is invalid
Form geersizse sipari dmesini kapatmak iin genel formun geersiz olup olmadn renmem gerekiyor.
and how do we find this out? In the end,
Ve bunu sonunda nasl bulacaz.
there are of course a couple of ways, we could for example add a controls array to our orderForm and now
rnein, sipari formumuza kontroller dizisi ekleyebilmemiz ve u an iin tm denetimleri ekleyebilmemizin ve genel form
add all the controls to that and then add another property which is valid for the overall form and we
iin geerli olan baka bir mlk ekleyebilmemizin birka yolu var ve biz de kullanc
update this when ever the user enters values.
deerleri girdiinde gncelleme yapyor.
Now this would require quite some refactoring here and it's only one approach, we can of course also
imdi bu, burada biraz refactoring yapmamz gerektirir ve tabii ki sadece devletimize
simply add a new property in our state,
yeni bir mlk ekleyebildiimiz tek bir yaklamdr.
so after our orderForm which is this object, we could add a FormIsValid property which is false initially
form ekleyebildiimiz bu nesne olan sipari formumuz, balangta gncellemek istediimiz geerli zelliktir.
which we now want to update,
Yani bir
so whatever you like, you can use both approaches and then in inputChangedHandler,
Dolaysyla, senden ne istersen, her iki yaklam da kullanabilir ve ardndan deien ileyici girii yapabilirsin.
so whenever we type, I in the end want to check if all elements are valid right now and if they are all
Bu yzden sonunda girdiimizde, u an tm unsurlarn geerli olup olmadn kontrol etmek istiyoruz ve eer hepsi
valid, I'll set this FormIsValid state to valid.
geerli Utset ise bu form geerli bir geerli devlettir.
So here I'll add a new constant, constant
Bylece burada yeni bir sabit sabit ekleyeceim.
is FormIsValid also to false
Form da yanl iin geerlidir.
and then, I now need to check all my inputs for their validity.
Ve imdi tm girdilerimin geerliliini kontrol etmeye ihtiyacm var.
So here, I'll simply for a loop through all my input identifiers,
Dolaysyla, yalnzca tm giri tanmlayclarm arasnda bir dng var.
in updated orderForm, this is the state object which contains all my elements and I want to set
Gncellenmi sipari formunda, bu, Devlet Optik'in tm elerim ieriyor ve formunu ayarlamak istediim burada deiken
FormIsValid here, should be a variable
olacak ekilde geerli.
therefore, I want to set this equal to updatedOrderForm,
Bu nedenle gncellenmi sipari formuna eit olarak ayarlamak istiyorum.
select a given identifier, input identifier,
Belirli bir tanmlayc giri tanmlaycsn sein.
this should also be input identifier, singular and there, access this valid property,
Bu ayrca, girdi tanmlayc tekil olmaldr ve bunlarn eriimi geerli zelliktir.
so the property we're setting here in the end but here we're setting it for one element, here I'm looping
Yani sonunda burada ayarladmz mlkiyet, ancak burada bir e iin ayarladk ve tm
through all the elements.
eleri birbirine baladk.
I not only want to set it to this because then again, we would run into the problem that only the last
geerli olduunu belirleyen son kontrol olduuna dair bir soruyu tekrar zeceiz.
check is the one determining the value of FormIsValid,
Yalnzca bunu yapmak istemiyorum, nk formun deerinin
so therefore I'll switch FormIsValid to true initially and check is this given element valid and is
Dolaysyla bu nedenle hangi formun balangta doru olduu ve kontrol edildii kontrol ediliyor ve geerli
FormIsValid in general true? Only if both is the case, FormIsValid is updated to true
e verildi ve form geerli olur ancak yalnzca ikisi de geerliyse geerlidir.
and if this is false and FormIsValid was true then the resulting value will be false and FormIsValid
Ve eer bu yanlsa ve form geerliyse, sonuta ortaya kan deer yanl olur ve mevcut
will be set to false because false overrides true.
olan form false deerine ayarlanr, nk yanl deer geerliliini tar.
And with tha,t I can then set my state and not only set the order form but also set FormIsValid
Ve bundan sonra devletimi kurabilir ve sadece onun iin emir belirlemekle kalmaz, onun iin belirlenmi olan
equal to FormIsValid,
her ey geerli olur onun iin de geerlidir.
so to my variable here. So again, the right side here, FormIsValid is referring to my variable,
Dolaysyla burada benim deikene formunuzun geerli olduu doru boyut benim deikenime atfta bulunuyor.
FormIsValid, the left side is referring to the property in the state
ou iin sol taraf devletin zelliklerinden bahsediyor.
I want to update
Gncellemek istiyorum.
which of course is this FormIsValid property here.
Elbette burada bu kadife mlkiyet oluur.
So with that, we should now know the overall form validity
Dolaysyla bununla birlikte, geersizlii genel olarak bilmeliyiz.
and this allows us to disable the button.
Ve bu dmeyi devre d brakmamza izin veriyor.
So I'll bind the diabled attribute on the button to this state FormIsValid or to be precise, to
Bu nedenle tm ciltler Bayan Velayat iin bu duruma dmede bu gl zellii veya tam
the opposite
tersini belirledi.
only if the form is not valid,
Yalnzca form geerli deilse.
this should be disabled. So disable is true if the form is not valid.
Bu devre d braklmaldr, bylece form geerli deilse disable true olur.
Let's save
Kurtaralm.
this and let's see the result.
Bu sonucu grmyor mu?
We actually have to inspect the button because we have no special styling for invalid buttons and we
Aslnda dmeyi incelemeliyiz nk geersiz dmeler iin zel tarzmz
see right at the start, it is treated as valid
yok ve balangta doru kabul ediliyor.
unfortunately because it is not disabled.
Ne yazk ki devre d deil.
If I enter something here, this never changes,
Buraya bir ey girersem bu asla deimez.
so our button isn't really updated with the state of our form,
Dolaysyla dmemiz formumuzun durumu ile gerekten gncellenmemitir.
it's not really using our validity,
Gerekten geerliliini kullanmyoruz.
why? Well because we use our own button element and there, we don't know a disabled property.
Neden kendi dme elemanmz kullandmz ve orada engelli bir mal var bilmiyoruz.
We have to go to our button element and there, we can set disabled on this button and set it to props.disabled
Dme esine gitmeliyiz ve burada bu dmede devre d brakabilir ve engellemeyecek ekilde
.
ayarlayabiliriz.
So to that property I just defined because you have to remember, we are not using the original hrml button
Bu mlke sadece bulmak iin, hatrlamak zorunda olduumuz iin oradaki orijinal HMO dmesini
there,
kullanmyoruz.
we're using our own implementation
Kendi uygulamanz kullanyoruz.
so there we need to expect a disabled prop and pass it on to the native button disabled attribute.
Dolaysyla, orada devre d braklm bir Propp beklemeliyiz ve yerli putten devre d braklm znitelie geirmeliyiz.
With that if we save all files and go back,
Bununla btn dosyalar kaydedip geri dnersek.
now you see it's disabled at the start
Artk balangta devre d olduunu gryorsun.
and if I enter something here, let's fill out all these inputs here with valid data.
Ve burada bir eyler girersem, tm bu tweetleri burada geerli verilerle dolduralm.
So now it should become valid except for that it doesn't
Dolaysyla, imdi bunun geerli olmas gerekir, bunun dnda geerlidir.
so let's find out why is the validity not updated correctly. In the contact data component,
yleyse, iletiim verisi bileeninde geerliin doru ekilde gncellenmediini renelim.
it looks like we're not setting FormIsValid to true even if the whole form should be valid.
Grne baklrsa, formun ayarlanmas, tm formun geerlilii olmasa bile geerlidir.
Let's confirm this by logging FormIsValid here in the inputChangedHandler
Bunu, giri formunu geerli olarak dorulayalm burada girdi deitirilmi ileyici geerli.
and let's go back, open the console log and enter something in all these fields and you'll see, it's
ap bu alanlara bir eyler girelim ve srekli tanmlanmadn greceksin.
constantly undefined,
Ve tekrar konsol kilidini
why is that?
Neden.
This is related to our inputs,
Bu bizim girdilerimizle ilgilidir.
remember we have this dropdown which doesn't have any validation rules attached to it.
Onayl herhangi bir dorulama kuralna sahip olmayan alr mennn olduunu unutmayn.
Now it also doesn't have a valid property therefore
Bu nedenle geerli bir zellie sahip deil.
and if we then loop through all the elements and use this valid attribute, it of course isn't true or
Ve tm eleri tekrar etmezsek ve bu geerli znitelii kullanmazsak, alr men iin
false for the dropdown, it's undefined and undefined is always treated as false
doru veya yanl deil, tanmsz ve tanmsz daima yanl olarak deerlendirilir.
but it also never changes to true.
Ama ayn zamanda asla doruyu deitirmez.
So a way to fix this is to simply still add this valid property to the dropdown even though it of course
Bu sorunu gidermenin bir yolu, elbette herhangi bir dorulama kuralna sahip olmamasna ramen bu geerli
doesn't have any validation rules
mlk alr pencereye eklemenizdir.
but therefore it should always be valid,
Ancak bu nedenle her zaman geerli olmaldr.
so that's our delivery method dropdown. With that changed,
Deiiklik yapm olan gnderim yntemi alr mens.
if we now enter something valid into all these fields, let me inspect the order,
imdi tm bu alanlara geerli bir ey girersem, emri inceleyeyim.
if I now enter a valid email address here, you'll see the button becomes enabled.
imdi burada geerli bir e-posta adresi girersem, dmenin etkinleeceini grrsnz.
Now I can remove a method I added for debugging to my inputChangedHandler and now of course, we also
imdi giriimi deitirmek iin hata ayklamaya eklediim bir yntemi kaldrabilirim ve ite tabii ki de
need to adjust the button.
dmeyi ayarlamamz gerekiyor.
So on the button, we now need a special styling if it's disabled,
Dme zerinde devre d braklmsa zel bir tasarma ihtiyacmz var.
so let's go to button.css and there, I'll add a special class for my button class special styling I
Bu yzden C-s dmelerine gidelim ve devre d braklm sahte seici iin sylemem gereken dme snf
should say, for the disabled pseudo selector
zel tarzm iin zel bir snf ekleyin.
I want to set the color to this gray-ish look so that the button really looks disabled.
Rengi rezalet yapacak ekilde ayarlamak istiyorum, bylece dmenin gerekten devre d kald grnyor.
Let's also set the cursor to not allowed here so that the cursor also reflects that we can't click
mleci izin verilmesine izin vermek iin imleci de ayarlayalm bylece imlecin de bunu tklayabileceimizi
this,
yanstmas salanr.
now we're also showing that this is disabled.
imdi bunun da devre d olduunu gsteriyoruz.
Now let's turn our heads towards a tiny error you might already have discovered. If we changed a
listede sizi deitirip deitirmediysek, aslnda dorulamamza ilikin bir hata mesaj bulduumuzu kefettiniz.
value in the dropdown, we actually get an error message related to our validation.
imdi bamz kk bir hataya doru evirelim veya alan
Let's fix this error in the next lecture.
Bir sonraki derste bu hatay dzeltelim.